PROFESSOR: Let's see another
example of an MDP.
Much like in search problems, it's very
easy to think of these things in
terms of being on a grid, because that's
often a great running example
that we use.
So let's take the example
of a race car.
We have some robotic race car, and it
would like to travel far and quickly.
So we're going to imagine that this
car has three states it can be in.
Its engine can be cool, it can be
getting warm, or it can be completely
overheated and break down.
So we're going to show them like this.
So cool is kind of the good state.
As you get warm, you're
risking overheating.
What can the agent do?
Well, the agent has two actions.
It can drive slow or
it can drive fast.
What do those actions do?
Well, slow tends to cool
the agent down.
Fast tends to heat the agent up.
But there's some uncertainty involved.
So if you're cool and you drive
slow, then with probability
one, you stay cool.
If you drive fast, there's a
50% chance of warming up.
Now you might say, how come I don't
know whether or not I'm
going to warm up?
Why don't I instrument my car with
sensors everywhere and build a complex
model of thermodynamics?
Of course, you can always
try to do that.
You can always make your model of the
world richer, and you can always sense
more about the world.
And when you do those things,
your uncertainty reduces.
One, it's never going to go away,
because as we'll see later, your model
is never going to be perfect.
And two, in many cases, that's
not worth the cost.
In this very simple model, going fast
simply has a 50/50 chance of
overheating.
All right.
So that's what slow and
fast do from cool.
From warm, slow either keeps you the
same or it has a 50/50 chance of
cooling you back down.
If you go fast, you're guaranteed
to overheat.
All right, what about from overheated?
If you get to overheated,
the game's done.
You break down and you drive no more.
So a smart race car will
try not to overeat.
If you go faster, you
get double reward.
Otherwise you would just always
go slow, because why not?
So let's see what the
rewards are on this.
Well, all the slow actions
get a plus one.
It doesn't matter whether
you get warm, right?
In and of itself, that's not part
of the reward structure.
You get a plus 1 when you go slow, and
a plus 2 when you go fast, except if
you overheat.
Then you get a minus 10
and the game ends.
If you think about this MDP, it's
actually more important that the game
ends than what that number minus
10 is, because you basically
never want to do it.
So what do we see here?
This is a state transition diagram
for this Markov decision process.
It shows the states.
In this case, there are three of them.
It shows the actions.
There are two of them.
And it shows the transition function,
which says what each action does.
It also shows the rewards which are
associated with a state, an action,
and a result.
Now this is the kind of thing we
might have used Expectimax for.
And we can think about an MDP, any
MDP, as defining a search tree.
So if you're in some particular state--
for example, if you're in the
state where the car is cool--
well, you have two actions, just like
you did in an Expectimax tree.
You can go slow or fast.
If you go slow, you stay cool.
If you go fast, you might heat up.
And this continues down.
This is very much like an Expectimax
tree, but we'll see very shortly why
we might not want use Expectimax
to solve it.
You can already see hints of it.
What do you notice about this
tree when you look at it?
It's a big tree, but it's kind of the
same blue and red stuff over and over
again, right?
There's just not that many states.
So this is a case where Expectimax
would do a lot of work, and
we'll see why later.
In general, any MDP is going to
project these search trees.
You can think of the MVP as applying the
rules of a non-deterministic game,
and from any state, this is
what could happen, right?
I'm not talking about how to
compute things like values.
I'm just talking about what the
possible outcomes could be.
Well, you're a state.
What can happen?
There are actions.
The actions are under your control.
You get to pick one.
But there's a variety of actions.
From each action, there's
an uncertain outcome.
And so we need a very
important concept.
It's actually analogous to chance nodes
from before, but it's kind of
confusing when you first see.
It's called a q-state.
When I'm in a state and I take an
action, I end up in a q-state, which
you can think of as kind of the pair
of the state and the action, where
I've committed to the action
but I haven't done it yet.
So this is illustrated here by
the agent having decided
to move to the right.
But since the agent hasn't actually done
it, the action hasn't resolved
and we don't know the outcome.
So from a q-state, which is a commitment
to an action, there's then
a variety of possible outcomes.
What are the outcomes?
Well, they're all the states, s-prime,
that this action can lead
to from that state.
So these are the important concepts.
s here is a state.
s, a is a q-state, a
state-action pair.
The actual resolution where
we land in some s-prime--
that's called a transition.
And we're going to see these triples
over and over and over again--
s, a, s-prime.
I was in state s, I took action a,
and the outcome was s-prime.
That's called a transition.
It has a probability
associated with it.
That's T(s, a, s-prime), the
transition function.
And it has a reward associated
with it.
That reward is shown here as a gem, but
it could be positive or negative.
So that's kind of like an Expectimax
tree except, one, the probabilities
are given to you by the
transition function.
And two, the rewards, instead of being
at the bottom, are kind of smeared
throughout the tree.
They come to you step by step.